<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Network Security on Aditya Chooramani</title><link>https://adityachooramani.github.io/tags/network-security/</link><description>Recent content in Network Security on Aditya Chooramani</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Aditya Chooramani 2026</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adityachooramani.github.io/tags/network-security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>HoneyNet-IoT: Embedded Cybersecurity Research</title><link>https://adityachooramani.github.io/projects/honeynet-iot/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adityachooramani.github.io/projects/honeynet-iot/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;aditya@chooramani:~$ cat honeynet_iot_specs.txt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-project-overview"&gt;🛡️ Project Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HoneyNet-IoT&lt;/strong&gt; is an embedded research system designed to trap and monitor malicious probes targeting Internet-of-Things (IoT) devices. By deploying a decoy network that mimics legitimate IoT services, this project allows for the detailed observation of attacker behavior in a controlled environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-system-architecture"&gt;🏗️ System Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project utilizes a low-cost, hardware-centric approach to cybersecurity research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="core-components"&gt;Core Components&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoy Node:&lt;/strong&gt; An &lt;strong&gt;Arduino Uno R3&lt;/strong&gt; acting as a low-interaction honeypot. It emulates common IoT protocols (e.g., HTTP, Telnet) to lure attackers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network Interface:&lt;/strong&gt; Integrates with network hardware to expose emulated services to the local network or internet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logging Backend:&lt;/strong&gt; A centralized server that intercepts logs sent by the Arduino, persisting data for later analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-key-engineering-features"&gt;🛠️ Key Engineering Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service Emulation:&lt;/strong&gt; Implemented lightweight service responders that mimic real IoT device replies, increasing attacker engagement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Telemetry Capture:&lt;/strong&gt; Built a pipeline to record critical attacker metadata, including &lt;strong&gt;Source IP&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Port&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Payloads&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Timestamps&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource Optimization:&lt;/strong&gt; Optimized the Arduino firmware to handle basic network interactions while remaining within the strict memory limits of the ATmega328P microcontroller.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attack Diversion:&lt;/strong&gt; Designed to reduce risk to production systems by providing a high-visibility target for reconnaissance and exploitation attempts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-research-value--impact"&gt;🔬 Research Value &amp;amp; Impact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threat Intelligence:&lt;/strong&gt; Gathers real-world data on common IoT exploit vectors and reconnaissance patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vulnerability Study:&lt;/strong&gt; Identifies evolving tactics used by adversaries to compromise smart devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effective Defense:&lt;/strong&gt; Demonstrates how $20 hardware can be used to build effective security research tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-future-roadmap"&gt;🚀 Future Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement high-interaction emulation for protocols like &lt;strong&gt;MQTT&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;CoAP&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrate a visual dashboard for real-time attack heatmapping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale the network to include multiple hardware types such as &lt;strong&gt;ESP32&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aditya@chooramani:~$ _&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>